so do you want to sum up what you a
little bit of what you just said
yeah um it's interesting after now
this experience of um
i i think it was six times
having a conversation uh we had
three four five six two three
and finally uh only two people
um on the panel and my my question is
um
what is in the head of of the others
joining such an a panel and
confirming the interest of developing
some
something and and finally they
they don't show up and they even don't
um place a short notice
in a group saying okay i can't
i will not join my life changed
post pandemic problems whatever
so um i'm astonished i'm just astonished
about
the behavior i'm not astonished because
it happens time and time again
so um i think part of it is that people
get excited in the beginning and then if
there isn't enough people
and they're expected to grow those
people you know what i mean like you
invite a friend like we would have had
to take it on together to keep growing
and there maybe wasn't not maybe there
wasn't as
concrete of a mission as they would have
liked people want leadership but not
leadership
right they want someone to be like all
right here's what we're doing like we're
gonna we're gonna start we're gonna do
this we're gonna break into communities
at this point
and that's not what i'm here to be like
we're gonna grow something organically
from the base so
if this isn't good enough for you to
bring people to then you need to help
make it good enough to bring people to
and then it's i do think that we have to
play within the pareto distribution that
some of the people are going to be
better recruiters than others
and other people are going to be the
ones who make the product better right
the conversation better and move it and
move it forward and other people
are going to just show up week after
week and other people it becomes less of
a priority for them
and it falls off and then the issue is
that other
people don't hear about it right they i
didn't post in the communities one every
every week if we had it but we might
have seen it grow
um and then what is this what does this
become
right like the the first what is the
word like the vision of this
is that i want to live in community and
i don't want to have to solve that by
myself right i don't want to have to
start a community do all that work it's
not happening and i can come and be part
of a conversation
and so i think there's dozens hundreds
of people in game b
alone who want to move to community
right like if you look at
daniel schmucktenberger and jordan hall
even they're moving to community right
they're like how do we have a tiny home
and move around
and have an rv both of them have posted
on their facebook pages
that right that they're doing that right
now are looking into that
and those are people with much more
connections and money than most of us
but you don't need connection we need
more connections than money right like
we need to be able to say well
what does it take to start a community
together and
we don't yet have the tools to make that
easy
but this is the mvp like this is the
minimal viable product if you show up
and have a conversation and start to
generate what that could look like start
to make the connections
um but it isn't i guess it wasn't an mvp
because it wasn't viable
right people didn't whatever this
iteration was people didn't keep coming
and again part of that is that i i
didn't take it on to keep posting it in
the in the community's
uh game b space and nor did anyone else
and so that was that was definitely a
part of it i have enjoyed
having these conversations with you
anything i do in the future that has
community as a basis
i will invite you to
because it is it is an important and
important piece i just can't dedicate an
hour
a week to having only like a
conversation with one person
when what is coming out of this next
fire that's in me is like
it brings all the pieces together but i
only just created it last night so i'm
like
is this did i just break game b or did i
just create game b
i don't know because i've been obsessed
with mlms and it's a bit of an mlm
and i'm like do you know what an mlm is
i can't oh you're on mute but you can
just do you know what
no please please explain i'm i'm not
sure if i know this
it's it's a multi-level marketing so
uh amway avon mary kay
life um where you are they might not be
legal so they might not exist there
uh but they're one of my friends
recently got involved in doterra which
is a
essential oils multi-level marketing and
so i've been obsessed with like how do
these people think this
math works like the whole point is you
sign up to build a business
but like the exponential growth means
that even if you could build your
business the people you're signing up
can't and if they're signing up
to build a business there's a point
where it doesn't work anymore right it's
it's
broken exponential math it is like
anyway so i've been obsessed with that
for the last little bit
and there's something that sparked last
night out of what's happening in
together tech
our tech cooperative where we're we have
all of these people working on projects
but they need to get paid right like we
have lives and so they
we don't get paid to do together tech
we show up for an hour and we have our
own projects that we're passionate about
but if we could get paid to do our
passion projects
then they go from being something you do
in an hour a week to something you do
almost full time right because it's what
you're trying to do um
carrie came into the the game b space
and was more of like an admin type and
an organizer
which is exactly what we need but like
she needs to be able to make
at least a part-time living off of it
because
of the anyway the economy and stuff and
so these friends of mine needing to make
money
people i know with passion projects and
then this like broken broken mlm system
has sparked an idea where i'm like oh we
can attack
our needs from both ends with solution
raisings from the bottom
where we can figure out how to feed
ourselves how to get into a community
how to do
what we need to do and from the top we
can actually have
people retire themselves what part of
what's broken about an mlm
is that there's no cap on your earnings
right so the people who get in the
beginning
can make tens of millions of dollars a
month
and well they're selling that like like
i actually have the broken math on my
board here
if you see like the 32 they they're
trying to tell you that if you sign up
three people who sign up three people
and you get to the seventh layer you get
to earn 32
000 a month well that's a pretty
enticing number for people but anyone
who earns above that is actually taking
away from the people below them and it's
just um
what i'm looking to do there's a cap
right no one's making over 120 000
a year not a month a year so
we're effectively retiring people from
game a to game b
and while creating the things that help
create ubi for everybody
and so that's what is coming together
for it for me and my mind at the moment
and um part of that is meta community
i think what we're looking to do is
create lives that work for us which is
what mlms try to do
you're just not working hard enough and
you're not like it's all on you as it's
like you create the perfect life because
you could
if you tried you could earn 32 000 a
month and they do a lot of the
toxic positivity stuff of like you're
just not trying hard enough
um but if there's a space where we can
come together
and create lives that work for us right
which is what partly what we've been
doing like what would you want in
community
right what what would that look like for
you it's going to look different for
different people
what does your life look like what are
your hobbies who are you hanging out
with what does that like
beautiful life look like that isn't
about earning 32 000 a month
right it's about real things what food
are you eating
what things are you spending your time
doing what projects are you doing
and offering creating tools together to
make that more and more possible
and so that is so part of that is the
meta community piece right that like
there has to be a tool
a way to have a conversation about how
do we start communities how do we get
involved in ones that already exist
how do we do that from
um because and part of it is
if we had had a hundred people show up
on the first one
this wouldn't be broken right it
wouldn't be just the two of us because
part of it is it's like oh i have to
build it it's like
yeah you do like there's but when you're
in in the beginning
you take all the risk and in a game be
enterprises there isn't really reward
besides you're creating a beautiful new
world for everybody that is a reward
enough for most of us
but not when you know what i mean you
have to retire your parents
you don't have enough money to pay for
daycare and you don't it's like that's a
lot of stress
if we can get people a modest income
while they're working on these game b
projects with the power of exponential
growth
and anyway there's something that is
like i said is coming together that i'm
yeah i still have to do this the video
that i have set up here about the
doterra mlm before i can
erase the board and do my like i'm like
here's how we
save it and so that's just a bit of what
i'm coming to this for
with and uh we're welcome to to switch
over into the conversation of um
i believe the topic was covid19 right
how we
how community is post covet 19.
so just coming back to this
issue of this business model it's it's
illegal
in in europe and if it's discovered
by by any entity they
they try to limit this directly
i would like to give you a sample
because it's um
we had this
uh oh you're frozen it could be my
horrible interest
doesn't say it's bad no
failing in the community not having more
people or not
not finding people for this topic uh
let's put it in a in a sample
um i'm a handcraft worker in my
community
and i'm building houses and
you can see a handy person
as as a resource if one person is
working alone to create a wall for
example you need a certain time for a
certain
amount of stone if you have two people
and you count how many they can
work in in the same time
they um they will
move more stone so so they will they
will create more wall
in the same time you can say now you can
argue okay it's two people so they
should
do a hundred percent more but
in fact they are able to make maybe
um instead of one hundred percent they
are able to make 250
or 240 so whatever you want to
re-route from somebody who say i'm
working
i do hundred percent so i want hundred
percent
so the the only amount which is
available
for re-routing without
giving a handicap or cheating on
somebody who is working with 100
is this extra this means if you can
create
a combination of workers and
this teamwork enables them
to to create more than this two times
hundred percent
then you have something you can move you
can say
we can take it as an investment or
we can share it or we can use it for
marketing
or whatever but it is just this piece
it is not more and
this needs from the beginning a very
clever construction
so we know in in construction work
that to work in a team of two or three
people is
the best case for handcraft work
you are on top of the ladder and
somebody is down
you don't need to move up and down all
the time
so so it's this extra which comes
up if you build a clever team this is
what you can re-route or
where the group could decide how to use
it
but uh based on on on all these
uh talks about game a and game b
um i i look all this from this far
point of europe and um
we have a lot of talks about economy in
general and capitalism in general
i think you know milton friedman
and he said once and this is a very
famous quote actually
[Music]
used a lot in social media in the
european area
he said once you can
have democracy or you can have
capitalism
but not both at the same time
so my big question to all the people
uh interested in this game b topic
is how many capitalism you want to
implement
yeah i think next to zero next to zero
in capitalism as far as
that incentive right that like you if
profit is your incentive
it is that it's your god and nothing
else matters right so you will destroy
the environment you will destroy
everyone but maybe your immediate family
in order to seek that profit
and when you know it's a drug and you're
addicted to it you need more and more
and more
and you can get more and more and more
by you know
it's to get to the top most of the
people who are at the top
most of the people are sociopathic in
some way
right they're either toxic positive no
no anyone can do this
where it's like they're delusional that
like no that's not how capitalism works
we can't even all be at zero
let alone mega wrench right and with how
our
monetary system works but having
profit is the incentive is the broken is
broken
like it's it's where all of our energy
go into because it's like well no one
else has envisioned a better system so
this has to be the best one we have
and it's not the best like all these
little pockets of people coming together
and saying hey how do we work together
in a team so we get that benefit right
we get that omni win benefit
but the tools aren't there yet to find
your people right how do you
if you're a single a single solo worker
how do you find that team mate if you're
not easy to find it right how do you
find the jobs now you have to spend all
of your time looking at
you know i think you're actually getting
paid per hour i'm talking about um
if you're just creating your own
community that's not really a problem
you're just looking at what needs to get
done and doing it
but um finding your team right finding
the resources finding those things
there's a lot
of infrastructure we can create that
makes that really easy
right so that you're spending your time
doing what is enjoyable for you
and finding the people that make it
easier right that make it more omni-win
yeah um i see in in case of our
community i see
us embedded in in a game a designed
society and so we are forced
um to look for this extra
pro for this profit because we
we are taxed by the society and
um when when you are farmer for example
in in europe and you try to make your
money with
um selling meat
in a way you have to grow
and i was ceo of an i.t company in the
past
and the the only opportunity to
survive was constantly growing
if you stop to grow you are already dead
because just in this gap
between the past the present and the
future
this movement of growing gives this
opportunity
uh to make enough money for
for your living so you are in a in a
in a circle in a in a in a closed circle
and you are running and
running a spiral
without any um exit
in our community we decided we don't
want to be driven by money
so our currency is
donation but
having many visitors in the year
we have also many
[Music]
discussions about this people are used
to live in this game a society
so they compare
the amount of profit
with a certain amount of
security and they say if you don't make
in
a line of a few years profit
you have nothing for bad years
now we are in a very ugly time uh
thinking in economy um
it is not right we are in in good shape
because our way of life is not based on
making money
so we are not so much affected by this
but it's very complicated for people
coming out of a game a
society to see this
yeah it absolutely is and that's where i
think
game b is beautiful i love game b
but game b has to create something that
does not require people
can understand game b to be part of it
right if you have to understand how to
code and do all the stuff that facebook
did to put facebook on there in order
in order to be on facebook facebook
would not be successful
and so creating something that meets
people where they are
and gives i mean i did this tweet i
don't even know months ago where i had
this epiphany where like game b
my game b is game like that i get to
participate with all of these people
who are here to create an omni-win
society even if their ego won't allow
them even if their current game a world
won't allow them
they're here because they want to do
that and this is my special interest
like it's all i want to do all day every
day is talk about game b and like how we
create an omni win world that works for
everyone
and i found you know what i mean i found
the people to talk to that's not
everybody's game be
right theirs might be finding people to
talk with trains about or find people to
you know like if we could create what we
have found
in game b for everybody right
just just the connection in the
community just the conversations
just the like hey these are your people
the people who are here to do the same
kind of things that you want to do
just off just offering people that would
be huge right if if you're a builder and
you want to find a building team
you don't need to understand game a and
b right you can just find a partner and
you can see that oh i used to be able to
do this amount of work
now i've found this person and we can do
250 percent
oh wow right and even if it's just
sharing it amongst each other maybe
spain pending five bucks a month
whatever towards a system
it's giving you something right netflix
doesn't you're not
people don't join up for netflix because
out of the goodness of their heart right
they're like i want entertainment i want
is it worth
the 15 bucks a month to me part of it is
that netflix puts up their own content
right so like you're not really gonna be
able to find that anywhere else
and they have other people's content
that is like
we have to be netflix we have to be
something that offers something
to the masses that is a natural
attractor
that is like because i think most people
want to create game b
they want to create a beautiful omni-win
world they just got to come up against
all their to do it right like oh
wait but is that gonna hurt my bottom
line is that gonna yeah
it might it might but wouldn't you
rather know that you and your
generations are taken care of that you
have
food that you have connection that you
have community or do you want a million
dollars a month
which one like it's like you can't have
both
and so there are the people who want
just money
and the people who are like so
entrenched in game a they're not going
to be able to see
game b until it's right before them and
those aren't the people
like that we bring into the beginning
right the people we bring in are the
ones who are like
wow this like game b
if i had to pay 25 now that i'm in it if
i had to pay 25
a month or 10 dollars a month to be part
of it i might
right like i'm like it's actually worth
something to me but i don't know if it's
worth it to the rest of the world right
to bring people like we don't
necessarily have
have that but if we can create something
that is worth ten dollars a month that
is worth 25
a month um because you can see it right
like you can see that the
the community is worth it and that's the
product
right the connected community is the
product and the more people that are
involved in it the better
so the more people who come in and bring
their ingenuity
the better so like it's all
i don't know like it's already omni-win
it's already i don't know if i answered
your question or i went on a tangent
like i said i'm in the middle of
starting a new fire
so i'm a little obsessed
yeah in our case um
we have land we have places to stay with
us
in a in a bigger house and
a lot of times we have this experience
that
people are showing up for maybe a week
or two
they are on their own trip to search for
new life
they are desperate to find something
new they want to escape from the system
however they have their their ideas
but if you show them
land and if you say okay take four
stones
uh throw them away and everything what
is in between
is what you can use you can build your
tiny house on this
we will not charge you uh
to to pay anything to rent anything
and if it takes maybe half a year to
build this house
you can stay in our guest house and we
will not charge
for living with us
the people say yeah yeah it's it's good
it's interesting but
but how i make money
[Music]
i have not the skills to do it all by
myself could you help me
do you have some machines could i use
your garden
so um whatever you offer
whatever game b is offering people
coming from this
game a environment
i think it is a very big personal step
for everybody
because you have to flip one thing
if i go to a game e
place my first question is
how i could contribute to
this that after my visit
another one is able to experience the
same
positive thing and this is not common
um i i don't experience this as
common sense in all the visitors we had
in the last
years and this is something about 2000
or 3000 it's not
10 people
the issue is they don't want um
they want to create a life that work
that works for them but they're not
thinking about setting up
a life for the people who come after is
that what you're saying
they're not focused on on that piece
and yeah i think that's where we have to
meet them like i'm it breaks my brain
too that they don't think that way
because i'm like that's all i think
about i'm like why would i set my kid up
to be like a winner in game a
when what would give her the biggest win
would be game b
right like her and everybody playing
game b
that's the winning i don't understand
people can't see it but they were raised
in game a
right they don't it's like okay so
you're in it for yourself
and your family you need your needs met
i mean in that space where they come and
they're like where are the tools where's
the information it's like oh
this is what was here before right we
don't have the two we have these tools
we have this land we have but like
anything we do together
that you can contribute is gonna pay off
for everybody else that comes after
that if that's not an incentive for them
like i don't know what to do with it
like i'm like that's an incentive for me
it's like i would rather go through a
hard time if i knew that the people who
came after me are going through an
easier and easier time
especially since i get that as they go
through an easier and easier time
they're able to like
unlock their gifts and give them to
humanity and even if they're not
something i'm going to directly benefit
from
they are definitely something i'm going
to indirectly benefit from
and if the world doesn't see that and
it's not you know what i mean in
thousands of people who've come through
they can't see that
you start with the ones you can but it's
not even because it's like it has to
work for the ones who can't as well
right it has to work that you're
that as you work for your own
self-interest it's also working for the
betterment of the whole
um like we have to use the invisible
hand like instead of just saying it
works and like rising tide lifts all
boats like if we could figure out how to
use that as a tool and i think that's
what's coming through me is gonna do
because
it's like if you like i honestly don't
know what to do about the world as i've
said i don't know if i've said this
during this conversation but there's
that experiment that they would go into
a workplace
and ask you can get a 50 raise or
you and everybody in your workspace and
get a hundred dollar raise
and people pick the fifty dollar raise
for themselves
those people i don't know when you're
coming on board to game b
but like i don't understand you so i
can't work with you
right like if you would take less
advantage
so that you are better off than other
people
i don't know like why would you not pick
up anyway like i don't understand it i'm
like i don't i get the other ones right
the other experiments that come out it's
like
if it was the opposite i understand even
if i would pick
everyone gets 50 rather than i get 100
because the money it makes you know i
mean there's more money there
i get that other people wouldn't that
part i get but i don't understand why
you would take a position of
disadvantage
just so that you're better off than
other people when
i like i don't understand it but i don't
think
i think that we can create a world that
works for the other people
and they create something so beautiful
that it eventually calls in those people
as well
that are like oh i see i see what's
going on
i see what's going what's going on
in in terms of science you you could
argue with the game theory a little bit
there's a big difference between
a game which is finished after 90
minutes like
playing football or whatever and
an infinite game which is going on and
going on and going on
and i my impression is that in this
game a society the people are thinking
they are playing
games which are over after a certain
time so
they are looking for for the numbers
as a stockholder what happens in the
last three months
they want their their extra money
before christmas and so on and so on
because
they don't care about the future of the
company
or the future of the project and so on
so
the the things it looks like that
if in a in a in a bigger group of people
you have some people they are aware
about that we are in an infinite game
playing and it doesn't make sense to
look
for an advantage on a short term
but you are surrounded by many many
people
who try to make this short
cut for their own benefit um then
my impression is the majority of the
people they
they give up they say okay i can't
i can't continue to work against this
so um the consequence of this
is for for a community like our
community that we say okay we'll play
this
infinite game we don't uh we are not
looking for
short term advantage but the result is
that we have to um
to take distance from these other people
and to make our life much
more independent from consequences of
their behavior
and this turns
to something which is very slow it's a
very
long term project
even to find these people
who are willing to join this very long
term
project we are committed to our project
since more than 30 years
do you meet anybody between 20 and 30
uh willing to be committed to something
which will have
impact for the next 30 40 years
okay you have some mothers and fathers
and they want to start a family
but beside this there are not so many
uh interest in committing yourself to
somebody
on a long run
yeah i think you're right and i again
think that that's something we have to
play
in right that like if we can create
communities intentional communities that
are more transient
where people are able to be in you know
what i mean like
you have autonomy in your own life and
you can move your tiny home if that's
what you've built
around and and be part of different
communities for those of us who want
permanent community
it gives us more freedom for that and at
the same time
we don't want anyone in our communities
who are going to break them and
you know if the more transit the more we
have the freedom
and the tools to not commit
the more we're able to actually commit
like i have moved around
my whole life i have not lived in a
place
more than two and a half years before
living here
and there were places i lived multiple
in a year so when i moved to this place
like i never decorate
i never paint i never do any of those
things i never know how
long of a commitment i'm there for i've
lived in this house
almost nine years and so it's like oh if
i had known that i might have put more
you know what i mean it's always like
but am i gonna live here another nine
probably not so why put the time in i
put the energy in
um if somebody else if it was their
passion to decorate my house right
they enjoyed it and they worked with me
um i would absolutely love that but it's
like for me to put that
in is like oh that's whereas there's
other things that i've done
like planting blackberry bushes in the
back that are not
prickly because we have all the prickly
ones and i'm planting the ones that
aren't
it's like oh this is going to take a few
years to actually grow
even if it's not for me and it's for the
next people yeah okay i'll i'll grow
that
so it's it's interesting the perception
of how long i'm here for
and at the same time i'm like ready to
move now like i'm ready to
find something that is more rural and
more and i'm not willing to let this go
as well because it's it's
i've been here nearly a decade which is
why rent is cheap which is why
there's there i feel like this is my
neighborhood even though i don't know my
neighbors i know the space
and so it feels like that
but finding like working with the
problem is people don't even know what
they want right so those people who've
come
through i don't know if they would have
that same story right they wouldn't be
like well i didn't know how to make a
house they may
they may right that might be why they
why they left
um in which case if we're able to to
gather that data and there's enough of
us who are like i don't know how to
build a house
we can concentrate that information and
and give them you know a diy
course on how you build your own house
and a community of people who are doing
the same thing to build their own houses
even if they're not in the same space
right
if they were connected to people all
over the world who are building their
own space in between four rocks
right they might
they it would be easier but to like take
that on when you're like i can't
possibly grow my own food i can't
possibly build my own house i i know i
feel that way
by myself i need people i need community
and so to be able to to be in that and
and not be wrong for that
right like no one taught me how to build
a house and i have more construction
experience than most people
i've you know built a house of habitat
for humanity we built a garage when i
was in high school
with our shop class i've been in shop
class right so
um and still i'm like okay i need other
people to like figure i don't remember
how to use a table saw i don't remember
how to do those things i want to build a
cob house they're beautiful but i don't
know if i could build one beautifully
that there's like a way to work with
people and not make them wrong now if
they're like no i don't want to spend
six months of my time building a house
are you kidding me no i want to go and
make millions of dollars and pay someone
else to do it and i don't
like that's a different feeling than
like i don't know how
like that seems overwhelming to me and
to honor that overwhelm is okay
we're supposed to be in this together
we're supposed to figure this out
together
how do we how does my effort
add to the whole so that less p so we
have less effort right how do we get
that 250 percent
it's not me starting a whole community
and falling apart and no one gets the
information on why it fell apart or any
of that information
creating meta community creating that
space that is like
let's share in the ingenuity let's share
in the passion
and there's ways especially with the
internet right where like if you have a
blueprint for a home
and you're willing to share that anyone
can build that right
especially if as you're building and be
like i don't understand this piece
you have other people who've built it
who can help you do that
and um the less people have to be paid
for their time
right where it's like no this is my i
already live in a house that i
own right i don't you know what i mean
like i built it i've been here six
months i already live in a house that i
own
where can i spend my time doing what i
love if it happens to be giving back in
that in that way that i
just became obsessed with tiny homes and
now i want to help everyone live in a
tiny home or everyone live in a cob
house
then that's going to be where i
naturally put my time and therefore it's
going to be
a more natural match
okay uh thinking about sharing something
in
in relation to building a house um i can
imagine
in the future when you have um cnc
solutions to plot your house you can
share
the raw data
so somebody could set up
a house you could decide which
data set you would choose and uh maybe
it's public domain
so um it's for free um you have no
copyright
no interest today um
whatever is with with legal issues
between different countries but um
i think when when i look back in our
community
we we try to empower people so we had a
lot of people coming
from office with without any
any knowledge in handcraft and they
experienced
themselves their own body their own
mental status
in in doing something with their hands
in creating something and they get
they became so enthusiastic with doing
these things that
finally some of them they
left our place and they created
their own little place so we empowered
them to to feel
enough strength to to start to
rebuild a house an old house to
or or even to build a new one
so to to set up a place where you can
try
without a risk where you can fail
without being punished
a kind of place
related to informal education in which
you can
experience yourself this is something
people need even youth need this
a lot um we try to do it we try our best
and hope hopefully we have more of these
places
um uh just yesterday i had a talk with
the father of three kids in philadelphia
and um they are on the way to
together some positive swords
for a better reset after this pandemic
event
and we came back
and back again and all also he said
most of my panels
are driven by people who say we need to
empower
the people so in instead of stealing
the power instead of
exploitation to
to show them what what they can do by
themselves
i think this is a big thing to do even
after this pandemic event
to to to use all this
um this energy with
which is free now because people have no
labor no jobs
they are desperate what to do
so to show them that they can do a lot
with their own energy this is
um something we should
we should create bridges to this
yeah i think if there was a space where
people could come and talk about
what they're feeling right that that
like
trust in that the system is being held
up and that like
our governments have it we're gonna have
houses we're gonna have food we're gonna
have and like watching that kind of
crumble
and so like oh wait i need a job to be
able to pay for food
i need a job to be able to pay my rent
and there's no jobs
that they're you know and to be able to
empower people to say
okay you're right you might never be
able to get a million dollar mortgage
and pay it off it's
world might be gone but you could build
one right you could build one with your
two hands and
that feels daunting it definitely feels
daunting to me
but what if you were working with other
people who had skills right what if like
what you're doing is putting in
i don't know how long it takes to build
a house you'd probably be much much more
like how many hours it takes to build a
house
but if you're putting that in times
three to other people's houses
right where it's like building my own
sounds very daunting
but learning on somebody else's
right without building it from scratch
for them and be like here's the thing
that falls apart
like pinterest failed a tiny house that
i'm working with someone who
i'm the sous chef right like yeah i can
cut these boards yeah i can do that part
and and offering the labor for that
getting really good at a piece of that
um and being able to same with the food
right how do we grow our own food well
like
i'm growing a garden right now and it
has food in it has some food
it's not i definitely couldn't live off
my garden it's like the odd tomato here
in strawberries
but it feels really good be able to grow
a garden
this year like i'm really enjoying it
i would like to do more of that i would
like to build my own tiny house but like
oh
i don't have the money to put resources
in right like the the money to put
like buy the lumber or do any of that
actually that's not true it depends on
how much it is i might be able to do
that
but not and pay somebody to labor not
and do that the more that there's a
space
to share in the the information to
feedback the data and be like oh turns
out you shouldn't grow cucumbers like
this because they turn out like this or
they don't
grow at all that to be able to feed back
in the data
and to be able to feel like even if you
fail
you're still part of a community right
like oh this
we did do horrible in this tiny home
like here's what i would do differently
if i did it from scratch again
and offer that to the next group and the
next group um
my people build their house where you
are like is it a physical
permanent structure that they build or
is it like a tiny home that they can
bring with them
in spain we have like in many countries
in europe
a very special situation you can't
imagine this
on one side the people are used here to
build houses
they survive without any big maintenance
for 700 1000 years
so it's totally different material what
we are using
stones soil natural materials
in in the last 100 years maybe also
artificial materials like steel or
concrete but it's not so um
not so healthy on one side and um
it needs much more attention
on the other side also so here are a lot
of
abandoned houses here a lot of abandoned
villages
i think for the next hundred years the
tiny houses are not a big issue
in spain because you have so many
abandoned houses you don't need to build
one you just need to repair the roof
and find windows and so on and so on
and even you have a very very
interesting situation you have a
situation where
young people moving
leaving a big cities and
they discover these old abandoned houses
or
entire villages and there are maybe some
old people around
they know a lot about these old
materials and these old constructions
so they are very useful and very happy
that somebody is asking for their
knowledge
so uh when you imagine you see
uh 10 old men sitting under a tree
in the shadow in spain you can
write big data
on top of them because what they know
about
building what they know about handcraft
is a lot
and they give for free just for fun
because
they know every young person every
um young family moving to such a
village in the mountains um brings back
life to this entity and these little
communities they are suffering from
people in the last hundred years they
left for
labor for searching for jobs in the
coastline in the big cities
so here i i don't think we need to
build new houses we have already a lot
and all these houses also they have
a lot of history so it's quite
interesting
um to continue something
which is started maybe
uh 500 600 years ago
yeah that's amazing but what i was
asking physically where you are you had
said that you have a guest house and
then someone can come and build a house
there
when they're building a house it's a
permanent structure that they're
building or they're building a tiny home
no um everything is possible we are
building some
sculptures which are big enough
to to use space inside of the sculpture
and we we are building temporarily
things and we have also ruins
with this history so if somebody would
show up and say i would
like to use this ruin to set up
my tiny house based on a structure
with hundreds or thousand years of
history
they could do it it's enough and
and it's it's not a question of money it
is a question of
um faith
i love it because i was just thinking
for like the
growing for building something for
people who come after
right some of the reason people might
not want to come and build their own
houses they're like well what if we
don't get along and then i have to live
next to you it's like
actually even if you build a place and
it falls apart
not the place falls apart but the
relationship falls apart and you want to
move on or you just there's something
better calling to you
something different calling to you that
you build a place means that someone
else can come
and live there right like now you have
multiple guest homes for someone to
build
someone can just move in and start
growing food or start doing
the other things that
and i think people are starting to see
this in um
with covid what is happening like people
who have small businesses and their
small businesses are failing
it feels like they're starting again
from zero when in actuality they're not
because they still have all of the
information that they've learned along
the way
right of like oh this is how you build
it like if you build a business from
scratch once
you're a lot more likely to be able to
do it again i imagine it's the same with
its
home that like oh i built this one oh i
can build a home anywhere it takes six
months
right why not go and build one in the
mountains in nepal
or wherever you know your your heart and
family are being called
that as long as nepal wants you there
you know like
finding places that um but then you have
that skill
right and you have a connection to a
bigger community like there it isn't
it's okay if you build a house and you
don't live in it forever
just build it so it lasts forever
yeah i think it's not not only
about building houses maybe this is
a very big part of a project of a
community
because this is a physical space where
you experience
the other people in our case you can
build something
just on the other side of the street
inside of the village or you can go in
the mountains we have land
uproad so you have no
direct neighbor if you don't want so
it's up to you
where you want to set up this house
but the other thing is for me community
is also a mental space
a spiritual space i i would not
recommend me as a very spiritual person
mostly i'm driven by logical thinking
and science evidence
looking person to try to discover the
world with these
techniques but i know
from a lot of visitors they need a
mental space
they need a kind of family and
for me a game b community
can't be identified by one
single location it is more a family
it doesn't matter where the daughter is
moving
where the sun is going where they are
studying or working they are still part
of the family they don't lose this
content
so for me a game b community
will be a community which has maybe some
physical spaces for long term
short term who knows but if somebody
inside of such a community want to move
to another place
for whatever reason you don't lose the
connection to the community he is
still part of the community so my
my dream is that the resources
like village or like house
are fighting in a competition for people
not that the people are fighting in a
competition for the resource
i like it don't quite know how it works
but i like it
and yeah that that meta community that
idea that you can
physically move communities and still be
part of a bigger community
and i think game b is
creating that like at least it is for me
when i think about everyone i've
interacted with
on video for game b
there might be many i don't want to live
with right like in community
um there are very few actually but
there might be many who don't want to
live with me that would maybe a
different
a different scenario but that doesn't
mean i don't want them part of my
community my bigger community
right of like okay we might butt heads
all of the time but that means we're
maybe not going to be in a physical
community together
but i'm absolutely okay helping you
build your tiny home over there
right like there's i've yet to meet
someone where i'm like okay
if you got life to if life was easier
for you
it would make it worse for the world
right
everyone in game b i've met i'm like wow
if we could set you free
like if you were free from game a the
world
your life would improve and so would the
and because of that i extrapolate that
to the rest of the population and i
imagine that everyone's like that i'm
like
that there are very few human beings on
this planet that if their lives were
made easier
it would make the world a worse place
um but yeah the meta community of like
finding how to facilitate moving between
communities how to facilitate
the empowerment of building your own
home building your own community
and growing your own food without
needing to do it all yourself
um have you ever had a conversation with
uh he's known as liberate mankind
on facebook but his name's eric
have you ever shown up to one of his
happy hours or anything he's also in
spain
he's a an expat who has has a plot in
spain i don't
know how far apart you guys are in spain
he doesn't tell people where he lives
exactly
but i mean he has a garden has his has
his stuff he's kind of like
a hermit crate community right and he's
not a hermit at all he's creating this
like
online community and lawrence just went
to go stay with him
but it's anyway i'm curious how far
apart you guys are like if you lived in
bc
what you've just offered i would
absolutely i'm like are you freaking
kidding me i can come there
stay in your guest house build my own
place even without enough energy
so it takes me a year to build mine you
know what i mean like
i would do it even with if you don't
have other kids like even i'd bring in
the kids and be like all right who else
has a daughter around the same
age like if you were in bc i would i
would take you up on it
uh i'm a little bit wanting to take you
up on it even though you're in spain i'm
like
but i think uh um
and this is um this is something which
will create
a lot of difference between nations in
the future
after this pandemic um
the question will be how clever the
the political side will set up the rules
in case of tiny houses you have a lot of
restrictions
and a lot of people are fighting
and they waste a lot of energy and time
and even money for
advocates to to fight for the right to
set
up a house like they want to do it
so i think a clever entity in the future
a village a city a county
a country they are clever in this
competition
to attract people who want to do
something
by creating very
suitable law for construction
now we we don't have this
the the laws are more to protect
the game e big companies
and um to lower
this opportunity of young people to set
up their own things
just by digging a hole taking the soil
and using this soil for a wall which is
technically possible and these houses
are
very stable even if you have big
weather events so so finding
governments finding people
who understand that this new generation
they don't need a lot of
economical support what they need is
a law a peace the freedom to try
something without being punished so
this is what
i i know i'm talking to my daughter ah
okay
okay you are online yeah yeah i'm back
so just
uh maybe maybe to finish this hour um
i would come to bc uh um
if if um there is there are enough
people
to uh to set up something um
or i i would like to invite people
just for a holiday trip of one month and
together here and and to to see the
opportunities
in in using this
alternative design um in
in in such a community like ours
even i don't know if there will be any
destination in the future of
familia feliz in your country we will
see
i think one positive
aspect of this pandemic event is that
many doors are open and there are much
more doors open than some people
had calculated maybe in enforcing this
pandemic event
so um i think we are in a great time
we are in a great time to try something
and
we we should exchange by using such
platforms
uh we should exchange our our ideas and
knowledge about it
but also we should go in the garden we
should
take the materials we should use the
bricks and we should
spend some time in creating this future
not only
spending time on flat in front of flat
streets
i'm big on flat screens i live but i
also yes
growing a garden i this is the first
year because of the pandemic i was like
i don't know if we're having food in six
months i'm gonna grow a garden
and again it wasn't enough to live off
of but it's just nice watching
i'm a biologist it's not like i didn't
know that gardens grow
and how nature worked but there's
something about growing it where it's
like i watered it every day and it did
its thing
right it created it this is the only
like ethical passive income as long as
i'm giving it back to the soil as long
as i'm regenerating the soil which i
don't really know how to do yet
but building homes same thing like if we
can build homes in a beautiful way that
works and work i like what you said
about the governments and making it
easier i think right now they feel like
it's going to take away from them
they're like right if anyone can just
build a city if anyone can just like
they get that their citizenry being set
free from the
from having to work is actually gonna
cost them something
but there's like right but everyone's
waking up to this so what you don't
realize is you actually want to be in
competition for the people
like if bc switched their regulations so
you could build tiny homes or build
homes cobb houses
you could buy a plot of land and do that
as long as you were working within the
ecosystem
a lot of people would move here right
and then they'd have all of that
ingenuity that's created through here
and if you
end up generating money you are taxed
through it right like i mean it doesn't
mean you you can remove yourself
completely from it
but that there is that
they're they're going to wake up as we
wake up they will wake up because it's
like wait if there's
if we all move to spain right so that
we can we can redo the houses and build
there then spain is going to have a big
advantage
if we all move to bcbc we'll have a big
it's like who catches on first and then
once they catch on then anyone can do
that right once
once it's open and anyone can basically
go anywhere and create
create this community in homes then
it is it's like where are the good
people right where the where is the meta
community where is the
climate that works for you where is the
when were you legally allowed to be of
course we still have borders we still
have all of that stuff going on
but i think there is there's a lot
that's coming together and thank you for
doing this work for the last 30 years
because it is important work
i've been involved in intentional
community for a decade and it already
feels like how
how has this not happened yet like how
is everyone not living in cohousing how
is everyone not
but the pandemic makes a lot of things
that felt impossible before feel
possible
like i didn't think i could keep have my
kid home for the day for five months
but there we go we're there and a whole
other year maybe it is what it is
we're figuring it out as we go all right
i'm just going to end the recording